Hi, everybody, the United Kingdom was once the symbol of power and heritage because of
their 200 years of looting colonies like India.
The West in its predatory form came into India in the mid 18th century.
But in spite of all the treasure hunting, now, the UK is going through the worst economic
and social crisis in its history.
As of 2024, while the debt level of Germany stands at 63.74% of its GDP, Ireland stands
at 42.5%, India stands at 58.2%, whereas, the UK debt stands at 99.5% of their GDP.
And you know what's even more worrying, while in other countries, the workforce is getting
bigger and bigger in the UK, people are leaving the workforce due to long term sickness.
At the same time, UK's productivity has remained stagnant since 2008 crisis, the hospitals
are falling short of nurses, and 45% of the patients have been waiting in an emergency
for four long hours.
And today, there is such a big labor shortage, that UK has a shortage of more than 100,000
truck drivers.
And all of this put together, UK is seeing the sharpest increase in absolute poverty
in 30 long years.
So the question is, how did UK's economy fall into such a terrible situation?
What are the biggest mistakes that UK made, which caused this massive economic crisis?
And lastly, what are the lessons that India needs to learn from the fall of UK's economy?
This video is brought to you by scalar school of business, you can learn how to become a
brilliant business leader with scalar school of business.
The best part is that they have scholarships up to 100% if you register using the link
below.
People India's education system is so messed up that even after studying for four years,
35% of our engineers and 30% of our MBA grads are unemployable.
And here's where scalar school of business is revolutionizing business education in India.
They are offering a full time 18 month PG program in management and technology.
And this program is so amazing that it is built and taught by industry leaders who have
scaled billion dollar companies like Uber, Myntra and McKinsey.
And to help you thrive in this hyper competitive market.
As a part of the scalar curriculum itself, you will work on real world projects, you
will build your own business, you will take it to the market, generate revenue and also
raise VC capital while studying on campus.
And since scalar has been in the education industry for seven long years, they already
have access to 1200 plus company partners, which includes Google, Amazon, Flipkart and
more.
And this is something that no other business school can offer in India right now.
In fact, their online programs have been so successful that their placement rates have
touched 96% and their median CTC stands at 25 lakh rupees.
And now scalar school of business is handpicking only 75 students for their founding cohort
starting early September 2024.
The best part is that they have scholarships up to 100% if you register using the link
below.
So if you want to become a brilliant business leader, apply for scalar school of business
using the link in my description and in my comment section.
And now on with the episode.
This is a story that dates back to 2016.
And this is when UK decided to exit the European Union.
So on 23rd of June 2016, in a special election called the referendum, the people of United
Kingdom voted to leave the European Union by a 50 to 48 vote share.
And this is where the chaos in the economy started with something called Brexit.
The UK has voted to leave the European Union.
We got our country back.
The vote leave side presented a very optimistic view of what the British economy would look
like after Brexit.
Now before we dive into Brexit, you need to understand a very, very important part of
history and that is the formation of European Union.
Long story short, after the World War Two ended, the leaders of European countries realized
that if they act as individual countries, and if they compete with each other or fight
with each other, they'll be wasting a ton of money and a ton of manpower.
And if you look at the map of Europe, you will see why it makes sense.
Look at this guys.
The European countries are so small that if every country had to spend on military to
guard their borders, it would be very costly, right?
Similarly, if a country like Hungary wants to trade with the world, it would be a land
locked country with no access to sea at all.
So if they wanted access to the North Sea, they would have to pay taxes to Austria and
Germany because they would be using their land.
So in this futile race of defense and trade taxes, none of the countries would have progressed
well at all.
This is the reason why in 1952, six countries, Belgium, France, Germany, Italy, Luxembourg,
and the Netherlands, they all decided to take their economic relationship to the next level
by forming something called the European Coal and Steel Community.
And this gave them some incredible advantages.
For example, when France needed lots of coal and steel, Germany offered steel and coal
to France to help them in post war reconstruction.
Similarly, Germany was able to sell its coal and steel to other members, and it was able
to make a profit with steel products to develop its economy and to decrease its debt.
Similarly, countries like Italy, Belgium, Netherlands, and Luxembourg, they were able
to get access to countries with a larger population like Germany and France.
So all of these put together, the businesses in these countries got access to six countries
with no taxes or opposition.
This is how a small union of countries benefited by sharing both resources and access.
And this union was so so successful, that more and more countries started to join this
union.
And fast forward to today, it is a union with 27 member countries.
This is how ladies and gentlemen, in 1993, this union evolved to become one of the most
powerful unions in the world, which we all know today as the European Union.
And all these countries got three major superpowers by joining the European Union.
Now listen to this very, very carefully, because here's where the heart of UK's economic crisis
lies.
The first superpower that these countries enjoyed was the superpower of EU citizenship,
which means all the citizens of European Union could move and reside freely in any European
Union country.
Secondly, in the European Union, goods, services and capital could move across national borders
without any barriers.
So a furniture businessman in Greece could sell his furniture in the UK.
And there was no extra tax and no trade regulation.
And lastly, for the small countries, the European Union gave an unfair advantage of trade negotiation.
For example, imagine if a small country like Hungary and a giant like India sit at the
negotiation table.
Now you tell me who will have an upper hand in this negotiation.
India has a population of 1.4 billion, while Hungary's population is only 10 million.
So if we sit down for a bilateral trade agreement, we could tell Hungary that we will give your
automobile industry and access to a population of 1.4 billion if you reduce your import taxes
by 25%.
But Hungary will have to decrease the import duty on Indian automobile by 50%.
Why?
Because we are a bigger country and we can exploit a small country because we are giving
them access to a much bigger market.
But you know what, guys, here's where the European Union came in.
And they said, instead of an individual country bargaining with India, the entire European
Union will sit down with India to negotiate.
So now the European Union is sitting down as a single entity with a population of 447
million people.
And this makes them so so powerful that while India has a population of 1.4 billion people
and a per capita income of $2,700, EU as an entity comes with a population of 450 million
people and a per capita income of $52,000.
So now do you realize when European Union as a giant entity sits at the negotiation
table with India, the EU has a much better bargaining power against India, even though
India has a population of 1.4 billion.
So this is such a fantastic arrangement, isn't it?
Every country gets better negotiation power, better citizen freedom, better relationship
with European powers, and most importantly, you get market access to a much wider population
as compared to your own country.
Then the question is, why did UK exit the European Union?
Well, out of the many, many reasons, here are three of the most important reasons why
the United Kingdom exited the European Union.
The first reason was that UK thought the European Union benefited more from UK than UK benefited
from the European Union.
For example, between 2012 to 2016, the average volume of fish caught by the European Union
fishermen in British waters was 760,000 tons per year, whereas the British fishermen caught
only 90,000 tons of fish in the EU waters, which was eight times less than the European
Union.
Similarly, in 2013, UK's gross contribution to the European Union budget was around 17
billion euros, whereas they received back only 6.31 billion euros.
Now, if you look at the net contribution of UK, it turns out to be 10.76 billion euros,
right?
So if you see, there was a huge disparity in budget contributions among the European
Union states.
So this is the reason why the Brits felt like they were being robbed by the European Union.
How ironical, isn't it?
For a change, the Brits felt like they were being robbed.
If you know what I mean, that is hilarious.
The second thing that bothered them was immigration.
So while the European Union expanded, several countries like Poland, Czech Republic and
Hungary got in and because citizens could move across borders, many people started coming
from less developed countries into the United Kingdom.
And foreign population almost doubled from 5.3 million in 2004 to over 9.5 million people
in 2021, which was about 12% of the entire population of UK.
So the Brits felt worried about foreigners entering their land.
Again, how ironical, isn't it?
The Brits were worried about foreigners coming into their country.
This drastically increased strain on public services and housing, lowered wages of workers
because of oversupply of labor, and eventually, it decreased job opportunities for their own
citizens.
This was the third problem that UK had.
And lastly, the United Kingdom felt that they could easily negotiate better deals with countries
like India, rather than the European Union doing it for them.
These are the reasons why they decided to conduct a referendum to opt out of the European
Union.
So after the referendum of 50 to 48, finally, Brexit happened on 23rd of June 2016.
But but but, as it turns out, as of now, things are not going well for UK at all.
And this is what the situation in UK looks like.
The question we heard is what on earth went wrong with Brexit?
And why is UK in such a terrible situation?
Well, the first major hit that the country faced was trade.
If you look at the stats, you will realize that European Union was one of UK's largest
trading partners.
As of 2022, while UK exports to EU accounted for 42% of all their exports, UK imports from
the European Union was 48% of all UK imports.
So you can imagine how much the UK depended on the European Union for trade.
But after Brexit, the UK was no longer a part of the customs union, which allowed them the
flow of goods and services among the EU countries without any import duty or customs duty.
So after Brexit, UK goods got taxed while moving to every country in the European Union.
So to solve this problem, UK thought they could simply sign something called the free
trade agreement.
For those who don't know, FTA or free trade agreement is when two or more countries agree
to trade with each other with no taxes or very less taxes.
So the UK thought they could sign the free trade agreement with the European Union countries
and they could easily trade with each other without immigrants, without contribution to
the EU fund, and without allowing other European countries to exploit the UK.
But you know what guys, here's where the UK economy faced a big big problem.
And this is a problem that even India is facing in 2024.
So the question is, what is this problem?
Ladies and gentlemen, this problem is that UK and India both are not manufacturing driven
economies, we are service driven export economies.
So we don't make most of our money by exporting products, but by exporting our services.
While the UK exports financial services, India exports IT services.
So the question we hear is, why is a service driven economy so so dangerous?
And why is manufacturing better for India and UK right now?
Well, there are three simple reasons.
Number one, manufacturing industries can provide way more employment as compared to service
industries.
And this is for both skilled as well as unskilled people.
For example, while the IT industry constitutes 7.5% of our GDP, the textile industry barely
accounts for 2.3% of our GDP.
But if you look at the employment that they provide, the numbers are staggering.
On the outset, if I asked you which sector would recruit more people, what would you
say?
Of course, the IT industry employs more people, right?
Because their contribution is almost three times as much as the textile sector.
But you know what guys, while the IT services industry of India employs 5.43 million people,
our textile industry employs 45 million people.
And while the IT industry mostly recruits only skilled people, the textile industry
employs millions of unskilled people along with the skilled people.
So the manufacturing sector provides way more employment opportunities as compared to the
service sector.
Secondly, while the service sector is prone to more economic shocks, the manufacturing
sector is relatively shockproof.
For example, during the 2008 recession, while the financial services industry and the marketing
services took a massive hit, companies like Nestle, Procter & Gamble and Unilever, they
were not as badly affected because while the people could cut down their spending on financial
and marketing services, they could not cut down on essentials like razors, detergents
and baby foods.
And lastly, while manufacturing is easily scalable to increase exports, scaling a service
company is very, very difficult.
For example, if I have to increase the production of iPhones from 10,000 to 20,000 units, I
can recruit, train and deploy people within a few weeks.
And on top of that, all I have to do is get new machines and run at higher capacity.
But if I have to go from 20 to 30 clients in my financial services business, it is very,
very difficult.
And by the way, guys, unless you're an entrepreneur, you can't understand the pain of what I'm
saying.
So if you can understand this context of the pain of expansion, just talk to any service
industry business owner and they will tell you everything.
So long story short, the manufacturing sector has three major advantages over the service
sector.
And these advantages revolve around employment, scale and resistance to economic shocks.
But now if you look at UK's economy, 81% of UK's GDP is dependent only on services.
And if you see their production, it has been stagnant for over a decade.
And this is the reason why ladies and gentlemen, two things happened.
When the service industry had to comply with 27 different countries for legal and financial
services after Brexit, the service industry of UK got disrupted.
On top of that, they saw two major crises with COVID and the Russia-Ukraine war.
It's been revealed COVID-19 has dealt the UK's economy its biggest blow in more than
300 years.
The Office for National Statistics has revealed the pandemic led to a 9.9% drop in the country's
GDP over 2020.
The actions we have taken to sanction Putin's regime are not cost free for us at home.
The invasion of Ukraine presents a risk to our recovery as it does the countries around
the world.
We should be in no doubt behind Putin's invasion is a dangerous calculation.
So as we all know, two economic shocks resulted into yet another disruption in both the service
as well as the manufacturing sector.
This is the second reason why the UK is suffering, which is over dependence on the service industry.
And lastly, now because of Brexit, the UK is also witnessing a labor crisis.
Long story short, as of 2021, 200,000 EU citizens have left the UK after Brexit.
In addition to that, the UK has a shortage of more than 100,000 truck drivers.
And what's even worse is that there is also a shortage of 30,000 nurses in hospitals.
And in all as of 2024, there are 889,000 vacancies in the UK because of which sectors
like hospitality and transport are struggling.
So now UK is finding it extremely difficult even while the global economy is growing.
And to make matters worse, the pound sterling is depreciating, which is further causing
inflation and it is making people poor.
So all of this put together, UK is now entered into a vicious cycle where the government
is not spending on health and welfare for people, people are not able to work because
of long term illness.
These people are neither earning nor spending.
So again, the economy is not growing at all.
As a result, neither the government nor the businesses have money to expand or earn.
This is nothing but the cause and effect relationship between the government spending, public health,
workforce participation and economic growth.
This is the story of the European Union, Brexit and its impact on the UK economy.
And this entire story teaches us three very, very important lessons for the Indian economy.
Lesson number one, never consult stupid people for an important decision.
In this case, the decision of Brexit was not made by the economists of the country, but
by the people of UK who obviously did not know anything about running the economy.
So if you ask an unemployed worker if he should ban foreign workers or not, he will obviously
say yes, right?
Because that would give him more demand and money even if he is incompetent.
But what on earth does a worker know about running a nation?
So if you consult the people of the country for a critical economic decision, it will
lead to a disaster because a mob doesn't understand economics.
Lesson number two, there are many economists out there who believe that India can grow
by boosting its service industry.
But while the focus on service industry is absolutely important, it is equally or perhaps
more important to grow our manufacturing sector.
Because if we want to grow our economy and secure our people from economic shocks, it
is easier with manufacturing than with services.
And lastly, always remember, if we want to grow our economy in the 21st century, globalization
for us is as important as self-reliance.
So we must be self-reliant.
At the same time, we should not hesitate to trade with the world.
Because self-reliance is not equal to isolation.
These are the lessons that India needs to learn from the economic crisis in UK.
And I just hope as citizens of the country, you learn something valuable from this case
study.
That's all from my side for today, guys.
If you learned something valuable, please make sure to hit the like button in order
to make YouTube Baba happy.
And for more such insightful business and political case studies, please subscribe to
our channel.
Thank you so much for watching.
I will see you in the next one.
Bye bye.